[Music]
Charles Eisenstein has been writing
about the need for systems change and
personal transformation for many years
in books like sacred economics and the
more beautiful world their hearts know
as possible in response to the pandemic
crisis he wrote an article the
coronation there has been widely shared
the things that I've been foreseeing and
also fearing are all coming together at
once
so on the one hand the breakdown of
normal that gives us an opportunity to
choose what we've been unconsciously
choosing before we also discussed some
of the criticisms of the article whether
it bypassed anger and the need for
change in favor of making people feel
better about themselves is this not the
time for righteous anger I do think it's
time for righteous anger the the trick
that the controlling forces of this
world have used is that they again and
again divert the righteous anger onto a
false target and onto false solutions
Charles thank you very much for joining
me I'm familiar with your work and I
think it's about time we had you on the
channel because you write about a lot of
the same things that many of the other
people we feature on the channel talk
about in particular kind of systems
change and possible other operating
systems for the society that we have and
also linking it to like personal growth
and personal change at the same time
given what's going on right now like I
think a lot of people are recognizing a
few things one how interconnected
everything is and also how this sort of
idea about alternative operating system
seems to be coming into a sharp relief
for a lot of people how do you think
that this current crisis is is showing
it's kind of throwing into relief your
work from before yeah thank you
it's kind of hard to summarize it that's
why I that's why the article ended up
being 9,000 words I didn't try to write
such a long article but there was just
so much to say so there's a few
in it but one of the as far as like how
it relates to my earlier work I've been
writing about how change happens through
crisis even through a process of
initiation where the old normal falls
apart where we recognize finally that
reality is not what we had fought it to
be and that therefore we ourselves are
not who we thought ourselves to be
because self and reality are inter
interwoven we're not just separate
selves floating in an external reality
but our relationships are part of
ourselves in fact you could even say
that we are relationship and this is one
of the realizations that's coming out as
you were saying that we're all
interconnected
you know through the kovat crisis so
it's it's like the things that I've been
foreseeing and also fearing are all
coming together at once so on the one
hand the breakdown of normal that gives
us an opportunity to choose what we've
been unconsciously choosing before like
unconscious choices are are being
brought into our attention and therefore
we're being asked do we want to keep
going in the direction we've been going
doesn't mean that kovat is going to
rescue us from the path that we've been
on but it's at least putting us into a
into a liminal zone where the
reinforcing circumstances of our old way
of life are temporarily dispelled and we
can say yeah do we really want to
continue down the road of separation one
of the things that's that's being shown
to us like none of the none of our
responses to coronavirus are anything
new there are all intensification of
trends that have gone on for a long time
for example the migration of social
interaction on to the
like that has been happening for 20
years at least now we're forced to do it
and it's taken to an extreme or the or
the movement of Commerce online or the
regime of Hygiene and the fear of germs
or the movement of life indoors when I
was a kid we there were packs of kids
outside playing all the time and now and
and to be kept indoors was a punishment
like you're not allowed to go out and
play now it's kind of the opposite and
this did not all of a sudden happen with
coronavirus or the restriction of
political freedoms the censorship of
information the destruction of small
businesses like all of these things the
the increasing medicalization of life
all of these things were already
happening and now we get to ask do we
want them to continue to happening when
we're being shown what they are like
taken to the extreme my hope is that
we'll say no we don't want to sacrifice
everything for the holy cause of risk
minimization maybe we will accept a bit
more risk except that death is part of
life and no longer live in this regime
of control that seeks to to minimize
risk control every variable guard
against the world guard against each
other and therefore not even really live
in an in an attempt to forestall death I
was struck by one of the metaphors that
you used in your article cuz I've heard
it a few times now and it's the the
addict rehab metaphor
and I think it comes up a lot people
over it seems to illustrate things very
well this sort of idea that there's a
sort of delusional way of being that
maybe we're now being confronted with
and there in that there is a choice can
you unpack that for me how do you see
that metaphor being useful yeah so on
the one hand
the one of the approaches to addiction
is it's called an intervention where are
you by force if necessary pluck the
person out of the totality of their
circumstances that that make the
addiction happen like the the addiction
is part of an entire life an entire
lifestyle your surroundings and so forth
if nothing else changes then the
addiction isn't going to change either
so you intervene and and interrupt the
routines the relationships the the whole
way of life of the addict and that
doesn't mean that they're cured but it
means that they have at least a chance
to make other changes and to look at the
things that the addiction was obscuring
because addictions kind of work
temporarily at least they they dull the
pain they're they in fact they
originated as a coping mechanism and for
them and and the problem is that the
price that they take to keep working
gets greater and greater and greater so
on a on the on a grand scale
I think that we have a society that is
itself addicted to control addiction the
things that people use um you know as
there are pathways of addiction these
are ways to control life in some way to
control pain to control emotions to
control other people and so forth so our
culture our society let me say responds
to its problems through various
technologies of control or another
example would be the the piling up of
pharmaceutical medications each one
causing symptoms that another one is
added in to address or agricultural
technology where where
ders and chemical fertilizers destroy
the soil and allow pests to proliferate
and so then you add a pesticide and that
destroys the soil even more so you add
another one and another one and pretty
soon you're completely dependent on the
chemicals so the same pattern or
foreign-policy
you know there's terrorists you bomb
them or you try to keep them out and
somehow it doesn't solve the problem
something else happens and you need even
more and more and more control so
generally the big picture is that our
society is addicted to control the
response every time it doesn't work is
more of it and just like with an
addiction the price that we pay that is
gouged out of our lives and gouged out
of our souls is greater and greater what
is it in America like 15% of the
population or something ridiculous like
that is clinically depressed and another
huge chunk of them or have anxiety and
another huge chunk are addicted etc etc
it's like half the people have some
serious psychological disorder and what
do we do then more control mood altering
pharmaceutical medicines like will
control your very brain but at some
point we need this interruption to say
hold on here is this working have we
actually hit bottom like this is showing
us where bottom is going to be like what
what current trends are taking us toward
and that's why I have hope in this
crisis as well as a certain amount of
despair and despondency before we
started recording you asked me how am i
doing you know and like sometimes I'm
like oh my god everything that I've been
afraid of is happening now and I see
this timeline going into a dystopian
future where it becomes normal never to
leave your house like a lot of people in
this country
haven't been that disrupted because they
were already shopping online for
everything and everything was getting
delivered to their house and not talking
to anybody when they went shopping and
now you don't even need to go shopping
you can get deliveries to your house
like why do we even think we're gonna go
back to normal and how far could it go
could we see a world where even dating
is online and procreation happens via
sex robots where you know the sex robot
comes to your house and you deposit your
sperm and then goes to a lab and so on
and so forth like like and I'm not
predicting that but from the
totalitarian nightmare of constant
surveillance to the nightmare of
separation from each other like all of
these things are happening and so
sometimes I'm like I go through this
despondency but it helps me to recognize
that this is also it's it's a choice
point making our old trajectory visible
conscious and therefore we can still
choose to go that way but maybe there's
an awareness now that we do have a
choice yeah and you mentioned for
example the medicalization crisis in
American society and let's not just keep
it to America let's talk about sort of
more worldwide but you use the metaphor
in the article of the taut rope which I
think is quite a good a good one because
what it seems is happening is that this
crisis is showing it's kind of unveiling
a lot of the stress points for example
in the economic system where we've taken
out all of the slack and so we're
vulnerable to a shock like this also if
you look at kind of our immune systems
or the kind of medicalization of so many
people in America like we've taken out
the slack of so many systems and we've
we've got weak systems in so many places
and what it seems is happening is this
this crisis is kind of unveiling or
showing us the kind of stress points in
society yeah very fragile everything's
very fragile our financial system is
very fragile like hate me leveraged you
know so let's just know as you're saying
no slack
and even our psychologies you know where
we're not resilient the the Hong Kong
flu that struck in 1968 killed according
to some estimates four million people
worldwide the population was half that
said that would be the equivalent of
like you know maybe eight million people
coronavirus has killed what so far
60,000 maybe hmm like not even in the
ballpark and I asked my mother if she
remembered Hong Kong flu she need to
remember it
nobody was panicking and yeah like you
could say that okay so it's an
interesting question why hmm and I think
that it's similar to what you're saying
that that we were healthier
psychologically healthier in that we
weren't so afraid of death and so
fixated on preserving youth and
preserving life at all costs we were
psychologically less fragile and socio
socially less fragile and now our
civilization is just like yeah like I
said like this rope that's pulled
tighter and tighter and tighter until it
just takes a little little touch for it
to snap and if it wasn't going to be
this it was going to be something else
so now we're in it and this is another
thing just the uncertainty one of the
things I was saying in the essay is that
maybe it is time to release into the
uncertainty rather than to try to cling
to the old normal and to bring normal
back because normal wasn't that great
was it given the like the statistics I
was referencing about addiction and
depression and obesity and autoimmunity
like we haven't even been getting
healthier in 1968 people were way
healthier than they were at least by
some measures than they were in 1928
life expectancy in America in 1900 was
about 40
six years and in 1960 it was like 72 73
if so it increased by 25 26 years in
half a century and then in the next half
century it decreased by maybe it
increased by maybe six years and after
that it didn't increase in all and now
it's actually declining and people are
not as healthy overall either all these
chronic diseases have arisen that can't
be controlled very well like the
technologies of control do not cure
almost any of the major diseases of our
time they can't cure autoimmunity they
can't really cure heart disease they
can't cure diabetes they can't cure
cancer I mean sometimes you can but
overall I cancer is still the number two
killer you can kind of control them but
you can't cure them you can't win this
triumph that was part of the ideology of
the onward march of science and onward
march of Medicine we were supposed to
have no disease by the year 2000 that
was that was the future that was the
shining future when I was a kid like it
was gonna be awesome the future and the
future never came so there's also this
another thing that I didn't write about
in the essay that much but that's really
coming up you know with all of these you
could call them conspiracy theories or
you could call them alternate narratives
what's becoming visible is incredible
distrust in the authorities a lot of
people just don't really believe what
they're being told by scientific and
political authority and this is also
like this would not have happened
in the late 60s you know or even up
until maybe 20 years ago people would
generally believed that there was a
consensus about what was true what was
real in society and a broad consensus
not anymore a lot of I mean a lot of
people are kind of going along with it
but underneath I think there's a lot of
skepticism and especially among like
working-class people why would you
believe what you're being told when you
when you feel like you've been betrayed
by the very authorities that you're
supposed to listen to the authorities
that were supposed to be preparing this
marvelous future for us to live in and
it's just gotten worse not only his
health gotten worse but people's
economic situation has gotten worse
every generation was better off than
their parents until this generation I'm
worse off than my parents and a lot of
my peers are and I'm Generation X I mean
down the road it's even like Millennials
I mean you know forget like trying to
own your own house or anything like that
the inequality of income is intensified
to the to the an extreme so yeah I think
the end of the world as we know it
doesn't have to be a bad thing but it
can be a very bad thing one question I'd
ask is is there a danger of confirmation
bias in that you've been writing about
these things for a very long time and
now we we have this situation and this
danger of saying AHA see I was right all
along is there a concern there of just
sort of seeing things through a
particular lens that that you've you've
already built up there's a lot of
confirmation bias going on I mean that's
how conspiracy narratives are built you
you kind of screen out the things that
don't fit the narrative you take in the
things that do you interpret things in
order that they fit the narrative and
it's you know anything that contradicts
it you examine it
rigorously and make sure you know who's
saying that and what and and could the
speed just propaganda and so forth and
anything that you agree with that you
take that in on critically the thing is
the mainstream does the exact same thing
on an institutional level science is
subject to tremendous confirmation by us
otherwise
how could we have been told for 30 or 40
years that dietary cholesterol causes
heart disease when it's utterly not true
and finally after 40 years of certainty
that orthodoxy is dissolving so
confirmation bias and other forms of
cognitive bias are rampant in the corona
virus outbreak both within the
mainstream and and it's not like there's
you know conspiratorial overlords who
are directing the confirmation bias
maybe there are I don't know like this
is um like I can go there but it's just
the tilt of the playing field toward a
certain narrative so that you know if um
you know say if there is a hospital
that's that's being overwhelmed like
that gets in the news and if there's one
that's not being overwhelmed and that's
laying off doctors because there's you
know not enough for them to do because
there's no traffic fatalities anymore or
something like that or people are being
forced to stay home if it's not
essential and that doesn't get in the
news so the media creates a nasteria
that is far out of proportion to the
actual number of deaths or even the
actual risk and you don't need somebody
to mandate that that SIOP is gonna
happen in order for it to happen
as for my own confirmation bias I mean
I've been going through I've I've gone
into there like whichever these
narratives that I type I'm reading I'm
I am I go through this
turmoil this doubt of like oh my god
maybe that's right
maybe I'm totally wrong how do I know
that I'm right how do I know that this
epidemic pandemic whatever you call it
isn't as bad as we're being told do I
actually know that maybe it's gonna be
worse than we're being told why do i why
do i as Daniel smackin Berger wrote in a
beautiful little post how do I know that
what I believe is true most people and
I'll not exempt from this choose their
data points in order that they fit
existing beliefs in order that they
confirm that I've been right all along
in order that they reinforce a familiar
worldview and a familiar self-image
anything that doesn't fit that is an
attack it's an attack of my identity so
it actually takes a bit of courage and
humility to entertain narratives that
contradict what you had believed in the
past and it's a shock and people going
to denial when when it happens maybe
there's a lot of denial going on right
now but denial is a phase you know it's
part of a larger process eventually the
the denial is harder and harder to
maintain and you enter the next phase
ultimately accepting that you don't know
and that is similar to the acceptance of
death actually
it's the same fear of the unknown fear
of transcending who you are right now
and that fear the fear of death has
governed our society increasingly for a
long time which is inevitable from the
story of self that prevails in our
society a separate self in a world of
other
if that's what you accept being to be
then death is the worst possible outcome
it's the annihilation of all that is all
yourself the universe itself and so of
course we have a medical system and an
entire narrative now that's all about
saving lives yeah you mentioned in the
article about death aversion and how
that's one of the the dynamics that's
going on and that I think you pretty
much say that we're going to have to
come to terms with what freedoms are we
prepared to forego in exchange for some
acceptance of risk would you is that
about right it's some a matter of
conflicting values you know like when we
hold life sacred and we hold our beloved
fellow beings our parents our
grandparents people who are
immunocompromised I mean these people
are equally sacred and equally worthy of
life as anybody else and so that's a
value that we should do whatever it
takes to protect these people like my
mother is in this category she's in her
late 70s she's had cancer she's frail if
she got kovin 19 she would probably die
and she's loving life probably you know
she just wrote her obituaries the other
day like she's probably not gonna live
that much longer
um but who knows maybe she'll be with us
for several more years and she's loving
every day of her life she's like oh the
sunshine it's so beautiful you know she
if she can sit in the sunshine and hear
a bird singing she is totally content
with that every day is precious to her
and I value that and I want her to have
if if if she can have six more months of
that I want that and I'm willing not to
visit her for alone fur
this month in order to keep her safe but
would I be willing to not visit her for
six months or a year and what I'd be
willing to and maybe never see her again
would that be worth it would I be
willing to tell the whole world to stop
to stop gathering just so that my mother
can survive no I don't think so I don't
think that that's so there's other
values here that that it's always a
trade-off of values like what are we
willing to sacrifice to keep these
precious ones safe are we willing it you
know to practice social distancing
forever if it reduces the death rate and
in and makes average life expectancy six
months higher I mean a lot of people who
are dying of Kovan are you gonna die
anyway I mean everyone's gonna die
anyway but you know in Italy for example
the median age of death was like 80 it's
been 80 so that means that half the
people who have died are over 80 well
life expectancy in Italy is around 80
anyway so so these people you know on
average who are who have been dying of
coronavirus could have maybe they had an
average of six months to live anyway or
who knows you know is is it worth
totally changing the way that we live in
order to postpone death a little bit
sometimes it is like there are times
where I would be like yeah mom I'm sorry
I'm not going to visit you because it'll
be over in a few weeks and then I'll be
able to visit you like it's a worthwhile
sacrifice but we have to be clear that a
lot of the rationale for social
distancing quarantines and so forth
isn't gonna go away the virus I mean
okay maybe this virus will subside but
there's always a possibility of a mutant
variation of it or another one or this
the flu
or there's always gonna be a reason to
maintain these practices or they say you
can get reinfected with it you know
maybe it's endemic we're gonna have it
forever so the questions that come up in
the short term are the sacrifices worth
it they're gonna remain with us in the
long term too and it brings up what do
we value do we value the prolonging of
life at any cost
or do we value play the exploration of
our boundaries the challenging of limits
adventure
I mean people make choices all the time
that are risky like to go to a festival
it's much safer to stay at home to let
your kid play out saket it's much safer
to keep them indoors to go to a bar to
get on the highway I mean there's
there's all kinds of choices that we
make in order to live life fully that
put living life longer at risk and I
think that this conversation about our
values is unavoidable and hitting home
for a lot of people like my friend
listen Rankin who's an MD she's saying
do you guys really know it it is like to
be on a respirator and she cites these
statistics like two-thirds of the people
who go on respirators for this die
anyway so instead of dying sooner
surrounded by loved ones they're dying
after several weeks of torture with a
machine breathing them in an ICU behind
glass saying goodbye to their loved ones
on FaceTime but they get to live two or
three weeks longer for a 30% chance of
of eventually coming out of that but
severely compromised it's not like
you're better cured you know like is
this conversation even being had the
medical system is geared around saving
lives it has no conception of dying well
house
do not keep records of did the patient
die well it's only the fatality rate so
these are just this is just the tip of
the iceberg
of conversations that we need to start
having right now and in the the article
you can you kind of as you've said
before you see it as a kind of
inflection point could it be a
transition or the beginning of a
transition to a better system than the
one we have or could it be could it go
the other way and I've seen a couple of
criticisms of you I saw Daniel Pinchbeck
wrote quite a long one on Facebook that
you responded to and I think his to boil
his down he was sort of saying that he
he felt that you were in danger of kind
of wishful thinking that it was that
he's more in the sort of we need to be
planning actual kind of action we need
to be having plans right now and he was
sort of suggesting that you were kind of
making people feel better but not not
giving them any guidance of what to do
in this situation I disagreed with that
critique I'm not saying that coronavirus
is gonna come and save us you know that
it's delivering us from the situation
that we've been in and automatically
gonna bring us a better world and so
take comfort you know this is a good
thing I'm what I'm saying is that it is
making our choice starkly apparent to us
it doesn't guarantee we're gonna make
the right choice but it is showing us
that for one thing like I was saying
before that that normal isn't even
necessarily where we want to be it's but
it's making our old trajectory starkly
obvious so and and also in the in the
piece I'm offering things like that part
about about death denial and a whole
other piece is about the the title of
that section was life is community
saying that that here's the irony that
even the things that we're doing to
prolong life don't actually necessarily
do it the things that we're doing for
the sake of health don't actually make
us healthier
like excessive hygiene which cuts us off
and social distancing which cuts us off
from the constant interchange with the
world that's necessary to maintain a
healthy immune system a healthy got gut
biome and so forth so yeah I'm not
saying okay therefore you know let's
have here's my plan for a big program to
introduce more probiotics into the diet
and get our hands dirty again and so
forth but I think that that's implicit
in what I'm saying when we take in more
information then our choices change and
what we recognize as possible changes so
that's and I think that as well if we
don't accept the opportunity that we're
being offered to take a step back and
take in more data points and survey the
situation from a larger perspective then
we're going to be trapped in patterns of
response that are actually a part of the
problem and the main pattern of response
is a bad things happening let's find
something to kill let's find something
to control let's find something to keep
out let's keep our world safe our world
of separation safe it's the same kind of
thinking applied to coronavirus as is
applied to you know immigration or
terrorism or a crime how do we keep
ourselves safe from these bad guys that
pattern of thought needs to be
interrupted we need to to take a pause
and we're being offered that not that
the pause is magically gonna change
things but that's not what I'm saying
I'm saying let's take in the full
spectrum of information let's let's see
what happens when the unconscious is
brought into visibility into
consciousness yeah I guess I guess sort
of following that thread my concern I
spoke to Joe Brewer the other day who's
kind of got a name for himself as he's a
complexity theorist and and looks at
cognitive science and cultural evolution
and he said we know that the kind of
more Machiavellian maybe the people
trying to defend the old regime the more
sort of sociopathic tendencies will be
activating right now they will be kind
of looking at how they like disaster
capitalism Naomi Klein's idea that we
know they will be doing stuff how do we
and people who are writing books like a
better world their hearts know if
possible how do we compete with those
people with the knowing that there are
kind of really ruthless people out there
looking for control of the situation
that there is a concern there isn't that
oh absolutely
um and so what I look at is what are the
ground conditions that allow those
people to even prey on the rest of us
what makes the totalitarian response to
coronavirus so compelling that people go
along with it
what makes the war on germs so
compelling like because these
psychopaths in power they don't have
it's not like they're superhuman it's
not like they have a mind control ray
necessarily their power comes because
everyone goes along with it that's why I
get down to the governing stories of our
civilization the story of separation the
story of ascent that human destiny is to
rise above nature the story of the
separate self the story of control that
comes from that like once you accept all
of these basic things then malignant
powers can leverage those they can
leverage the fear they can leverage the
they can they can play divide and
conquer if you are pretty so that that's
a good example if you are predisposed to
diagnose a problem as being caused by a
bad guy by an enemy then a manipulative
reader can come and say here's the
problem it's those enemies and we're in
a where this is war and so you're gonna
have to make some sacrifices to keep the
bad guys out
that's what Goering said it at Nuremberg
you know that yeah it's easy to get the
population to go along just proclaim
that there's an enemy and that they're
out the gates and that we that if you
don't go along with it you're a traitor
and you know he this is a this is
standard operating procedure and
and we have in our civilizational myths
and narratives fertile ground for such
manipulations to take root and the
antidote to that is solidarity the
antidote to that is a new story a story
of interconnection and interbeing
that says yeah is it really an enemy or
let's question that how am i part of the
enemy how i part of the conditions that
breed terrorism or immigration or crime
how is everything connected how am i
part of a viral infection like i
mentioned an article terrain theory
which it can be summarized by the meme
that I saw German your fish is sick germ
theory isolate the fish terrain theory
clean the tank so we have a very dirty
tank here we have like why are people so
susceptible to this if you look at the
the fatality statistics it's obvious
almost everybody who died from this had
serious producing conditions so that's
part of the dirty tank why why there's
so many diabetic people why are there so
many people with high blood pressure in
Italy there's the statistics I saw 75%
of those who died had high blood
pressure 35% were diabetic 30% had his
Kimia you know so so so yeah just to
answer your question rather than to
fight the evil Illuminati and
Psychopaths and disaster capitalists I'm
not saying we shouldn't fight them but
let me say in addition
- fighting them we have to change the
battlefield on which we're fighting that
dooms us - one defeat after another
after another and these ground
conditions go layer after layer after
layer layer into the structure of the
financial system for example based on
interest-bearing debt like that already
casts us into competition with each
other but down to the bedrock of who do
we know ourselves to be what's real how
does the world work how does change
happen what's possible Who am I
how did what is a good life what's the
purpose of life the answers that we have
been immersed in prime the field for the
regime of domination and control that we
live in today that's you know I mean
that's a big thesis to lay out that's my
first book the ascent of humanity I
wrote like you know 600 pages of
diagnosing that tracing our institutions
a world under control - the story of
self and how that story historically
developed I certainly I'm trying to hold
both of those pieces that potentially
this could be the beginning of a
transition I think it has to be the
beginning of a transition into a
different system but my sense is that
that's going to take a long time and
it's going to be incredibly painful and
incredibly difficult to get there and it
seems very difficult for even in myself
I feel this difficulty of holding both
of those pieces it's very difficult to
to look full in the face the like how
difficult it will probably be for us to
go through the the death of the old
system how how is it possible to live
into and live through that without kind
of bypassing it in any way you know I
look within and ask am I really ready
for the death of the old system what
part of
me I mean I've been you know I've spent
my life advocating assistance change but
there's part of me that doesn't want
systems change there's part of me that
was as a fairly privileged person you
know pretty comfortable with the way
things were
am I willing to step into the unknown am
I willing to step into it's a kind of a
death the death of what was familiar and
therefore who I was in that familiarity
am I willing to sacrifice you know
flying to exciting places to give
speeches that you know are moving and
inspiring and seem to be helping people
but do I really know that they were
helping people like am I willing to give
that up are we willing to give up being
able to just order supplements like I
like ordering supplements you know I was
you I'm using these like these
homeopathic energy medicine sleep
patches that have like solved my
insomnia you know that guy wake up in
the middle of the night and not builder
back to sleep and like wow I can sneak
through the night now you know and I
ordered these things online because my
credit card worked that could all end
and it could end in different ways
that's what I'm saying and it may not
end like we could have what I caught I
call call hippie planet you know where
everything instead of doubling down on
conventional medicine which is what
could happen if we have universal health
care from this it can become mandatory
health care I mean already chiropractors
and acupuncturists have been shut down
all over the country I cannot go to my
chiropractor
my wife is an acupuncturist and healer
people cannot come
it's deemed non-essential so like you
know we could go we could go either
these ways and in a way we're kind of
going both at the same time but right
now it's I have this sense of dread that
we've taken a couple steps down the
wrong path and that it's gonna take a
pretty dramatic shift for us to jump
from this path onto the path toward
holistic planet toward hippy planet
you mean that we've taken a step or
already during this crisis we've taken a
step down yeah I wanted to come back to
that just just before I do and Daniel
Pinchbeck mentioned this but I just
wanted to kind of raise it as is this
not the time for righteous anger like
we've got we've basically got a set of
authorities that didn't see this coming
that seemed to be behind to be kind of
mishandling it completely I see a lot of
people like Eric Weinstein for example
getting kind of calling for heads on
spikes and Daniel wrote also about maybe
this is the time for righteous anger for
kind of motivating and taking action to
create the new world that where I do
think yes I I do think it's time for
righteous anger the the trick that the
controlling forces of this world have
used is that they again and again divert
the righteous anger onto a false target
and onto false solutions so yeah they're
people there is a lot of bubbling anger
and there well should be because we have
been as a collective we've been betrayed
we could be living in an incredibly
beautiful abundant world right now there
is enough for everybody there's enough
of everything that we need for everybody
but instead we live in a society of
intensifying artificial scarcity
enormous waste side by side with
enormous poverty a million homeless
people next to tens of millions of
vacant housing units one in seven
children in America going hungry every
month next
to 40 or 50 percent of food being wasted
I mean I could give many examples of of
the obscene juxtaposition of
overabundance and poverty so yeah there
we should embrace the anger because it
is valid it points to a violation but to
then say but yeah to offer too hasty a
target for that anger risks replicating
that pattern of diffusing it by by
diverting it onto of a false target the
people who look like they are the
perpetrators they are functionaries
actually they are playing a role that's
systemic Lee necessary and if we put
their heads on on spikes guess what new
people are gonna come and do the same
thing that the old people did so Wes
have the right to sang to be targeted
I'm not even sure if targeted is the
right way to think about it the
righteous anger ideally will flush out
the truth it should never be satisfied
with a false explanation it should be
vigilant it should say anytime that it's
being offered a channel it should say
really are you sure because I'm mad and
I want it to change I don't want to to
run off in a mob and you know find some
scapegoats and string them up and not
change anything like that's that all of
that is a betrayal of the anger actually
so even the idea of find a target for it
that's part of the trick that's it
that's the diversion it doesn't mean
that things don't need to change but it
asks what needs to change so that the
conditions that generated this betrayal
and this violation no longer exist and
it could be that the best route to that
involves compassion and forgiveness
those these are not the opposite of
anger they are the result of the truth
that anger can flush to the surface and
this is yeah this is deep deep work here
but the anger is what can can keep us on
point and not be satisfied with sobs
with with booby prizes and this sort of
brings us back to the idea that we sort
of hinted at before that it does seem
that the orthodoxy like what it seems is
happening as far as I can see right now
you look at sort of the financial system
we might be seeing kind of a bailout to
dwarf 2008 we're seeing a lot of the
same kind of thinking just being doubled
down on again and again and
sort of sense that it the system is
reacting in the only way that it knows
but it seems to be doubling down on the
same kind of thinking and kind of
methods that created some of these
systemic crises in the first place can
you speak to that cuz I think you talk
about that in your essay there is also
signs of I mean in America there's a
moratorium on foreclosures and
addictions and that so that's something
that actually does help the common
people what we should be advocating for
in terms of a bailout is what I call it
debtors bailout as opposed to a
creditors bailout in after 28 20 2008
after that financial crisis we had a
creditors bailout where the the Fed and
the Treasury basically bought up all of
the troubled assets which are what like
fundamentally they were troubled because
people couldn't make their payments on
their mortgages so they were bought up
but did people have to stop making their
payments no people had to continue the
debts all stayed on the books an
alternative strategy would be to buy
them up so that the banks yeah they're
made whole the banks do get bailed out
but then the debts get forgiven and
we're seeing some some stirrings of that
actually to maybe forgive some portion
of student debt ultimately though the
only way I think to resolve the
increasing inequality that we have today
is through some kind of debt Jubilee and
that is profoundly radical because it it
redresses or it reverses a legacy of
oppression and inequality even going
back to slavery even going back to
to colonialism and indentured servitude
and so forth and kind of wipes the slate
clean so yeah that's that's that's one
thing I would like to bring into the
into the awareness and I'm seeing it a
little bit a debt some kind of debt
forgiveness like I mean this is part of
the righteous anger like this
recognition that I'm not supposed to
live my life in hock to the banks like
people you know graduate and maybe it's
you know in this country it's especially
severe but levels of debt are rising
everywhere like my life is not my own
I owe my productive capacity to these
distant distant institutions people you
know graduate from school with with
sometimes hundreds of thousands of
dollars in debt that they'll never pay
off their entire lives your labor is not
your own and of course we're angry about
that
when one or two generations before you
could have a working class job support a
family like you needn't have to have
both parents working you could have a
working class job support a family save
money buy or have your own house
eventually own it free and clear you
didn't have to be in the elite to do
that why can't we do that anymore
have we regressed technologically have
we lost our ability to build houses as
well no we should be richer it should be
even more accessible than it was two
generations ago but it's the opposite so
yeah that's something to be angry about
and that would be to answer your earlier
question a target a debt Jubilee is not
a target it's not someone who that we
can punish for our oppression it is
something that that removes the
conditions under which we've been so
violated yeah my last question is kind
of summarizes some of the questions that
I've asked already which
is how do we live and lead into that
better world that our hearts know as
possible when in so many areas we sort
of feel our hearts bleeding and we see
the world
burning yeah the title is actually the
more beautiful world our hearts know as
possible and you know the the word
beautiful was I chose that quite
purposefully as a different word ent in
support
in contrast to efficiency and the cult
of quantity that governs our society and
I would just offer that as as an
orientation and it plays into even you
know decisions about life and death
quantity says how many years can I live
Beauty says how can I live well it
provokes questions of why am I here to
begin with
I'm not gonna survive life I'm not gonna
have that on my gravestone
he made it till now you know that's
there's there's an illusion that we're
living in essentially that we're gonna
live forever when that illusion is
dissolved we can be in truth what comes
from that is unique to each person but I
think that as a society if we are able
to release that delusion which on a
collective level is you know basically
that we are here to transcend nature
that other beings don't matter that our
own survival is the most important thing
I mean this even gets into environmental
discourse
when we say well we're gonna have to
change now otherwise we won't survive
and I'm like well what if we can survive
on a concrete world where we grow our
food in these vats and hydroponics
factories and and modulate the
atmosphere with carbon sucking machines
you know what if we can survive is that
why we're here
is that is that the most beautiful world
that we can imagine yeah
maybe according to everything measurable
we'll be fine we'll have more gigabytes
of downloads per person more bandwidth
per person more life expectancy per
person higher GDP per capita but when we
when we reduce life to quantity then the
qualitative gets left out and this is
another addiction when the qualitative
is missing like intimacy and beauty then
we need more and more stuff to
compensate for it I'm not sure what your
question was or if I've answered it but
a brush with death can resurrect these
lost truths and I'm I'm holding that out
as a potential outcome of for
coronavirus that it is bringing death
into our you know putting it death in
our faces and thereby resurrecting these
questions of what is in fact a good life
and why are we trying to preserve life
at all costs rather than celebrate life
and live life fully live it beautifully
not just little long why am I here am I
here just to survive and reproduce and
maximize myself interesting go to the
grave anyway or am I here to make
something beautiful of my life so that
instead of leaving no trace I leave a
positive trace on the world and I'm part
this evolutionary project of life itself
to create more and more life and a world
that's more and more beautiful that's
the initiation you know that's a I
titled it the coronation as an
initiation into sovereignty into
kingship queenship the true sovereign is
somebody who is in service and is
consciously choosing that in service to
what in service to the kingdom in
service to life that is only possible
when death shows us how precious life is
because it ends therefore it's precious
and our society doesn't get that we
don't we don't embrace and accept death
we think we can move forever we think
that the highest goal is to preserve
life
preserve our preserve the self the
separate self which is actually not
permanent no matter what it's a huge
delusion and yeah maybe we're catching
in this pause we have this opportunity
to look at that and to choose otherwise
rebel wisdom was set up to make sense of
the world at a deeper level than the
mainstream media it was built for these
times of crisis and change which is why
we want to do what we can to meet the
challenge of the times more films and
also for our rebel wisdom members weekly
sense-making calls with our amazing
interviewees and also we're introducing
the wisdom Jim a place to practice some
of the skills that we've talked about on
the channel thanks for watching and see
you soon
[Music]